Leopold von Ranke Papers
Leopold von Ranke Papers
1765-1886
1828-1886
Ranke, Leopold von, 1795-1886.
5 linear ft. (280 items)
Papers of the German historian. Collection includes letters to Ranke, notes, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, and photographs, as well as poems and family letters to and from Clara Graves, Ranke's wife and great-aunt of poet Robert Graves. Also, bibliographic material about the library, compiled by Theodor Wiedemann.
149537
Biographical History
Leopold von Ranke (1795-1886) was a German historian and historiographer. He was highly influential in shaping the modern approach to history, emphasizing such things as reliance on primary sources, narrative history and international politics. He rejected the idea that each era is by definition superior to those that preceded it, as well as the idea of sweeping historical theories that attempt to encompass huge swathes of time and geography. His niece Amalie von Ranke was the mother of the British novelist and poet Robert Graves, whose full name was Robert von Ranke Graves.
Ranke's personal and professional library, consisting of more than 10,000 books, several hundred manuscripts and approximately 5 linear ft. of personal papers, was purchased for Syracuse University in 1887 and formed the nucleus of what is now the Syracuse University Special Collections Research Center (SCRC).
Theodor Weidemann, whose bibliographic aids about the Ranke Library are also included in the collection, was Ranke's amanuensis for the last fifteen years of his life.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leopold von Ranke Papers consists of personal papers relating to Ranke, his wife Clarissa Graves Ranke, and their family and friends. The collection also contains extensive bibliographic material compiled by Theodor Wiedemann about Ranke's library and manuscript collection, as well as a few items that were laid in various volumes of Ranke's personal library and found during cataloging. These items are accompanied by a note indicating where they were found.
The collection is divided into series, possibly based on when items were acquired. The OA (original acquisition) series was part of the purchase of Ranke's library in 1887. The Z series was purchased at auction from Sotheby's in the 1970s. The meaning of the other series (X, Y, GNC) is unknown at this time. Each series contains similar types of material: correspondence, notes, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, photographs, poems and family letters.
Topics discussed in the letters include health advice, child-rearing practices, administration of the English Poor Laws (John T. Graves was a district administrator), British Parliamentary politics, literary criticism and news, reception of Ranke's work in Britain, and the possibility of a revolution in England and Ireland in 1848, among others.
Other Formats Available
Items in the OA and GMC series are also available on microfilm.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into series, possibly based on when items were acquired. Within that, material is in no particular order.
Separated Material
The personal and professional library of Leopold von Ranke, consisting of more than 10,000 books, several hundred manuscripts and approximately 5 linear ft. of personal papers, was purchased for Syracuse University in 1887 and formed the nucleus of what is now the Special Collections Research Center (SCRC) at Syracuse University.
The personal papers comprise this collection, the Leopold von Ranke Papers.
The more than 10,000 volumes of Ranke's personal library, containing many works on historical, political and literary subjects dating from the 16th to 19th centuries and in numerous European languages, have been transfered to Rare Books for cataloging. They are accessible via.
The manuscripts, containing items in numerous languages dating back to the 16th century, comprise the
Leopold von Ranke Manuscript Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Historians; Ranke, Leopold von, 1795-1886.; Ranke family.; Ranke, Clarissa von, 1801-1871.; Graves family.; Wiedemann, Theodor, 1823-1901.; Historians, Germany.; Bibliographies.; Correspondence.; Lecture notes.; Legal documents.; Manuscripts (document genre); Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Poems.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Box 7, item GMC540, is restricted due to fragile condition. Researchers should use either the microfilm version of this item, or one of the two photocopies (GMC541 or GMC542, also in Box 7), NOT the originals.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1887.
Z series material purchase with Arents Fund, 5 November 1975.
Inventory
- Original acquisition (OA) series
  - E. Hilpert engraving of "Das Wohnhaus Leopold von Ranke's in der Luisenstrasse 24a.", OA1 (Box 1)
  - Annotated page proof, pp. 67-78, from Ranke's Englishe Geschichte (Leipzig, 1868), OA2 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified letter, 8 February 1886; OA3 (Box 1)
  - Notes on the Psalms, OA4 (Box 1)
  - Notes in Ranke's hand, OA5 (Box 1)
  - Printed folio, "Centenaire du Marquis de Pombal", OA6 (Box 1)
  - Certificate, "Seiner Hochwohlgeboren Herrn Wirklichen Geheimrath Leopold von Ranke in Berlin" (bookplate no. 26727>, OA7 (Box 1)
  - Indenture made between Helena Clarissa Graves and Leopold Ranke declaring the dowry for Clara Graves, OA8 (Box 1)
  - Receipt for Clara Graves' dowry, OA9 (Box 1)
  - Receipt signed by Leopold Ranke, 22 October 1843; OA10 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Ranke in his study, 1884; OA11 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified letter, found laid in Regesta chronologico diplomatica: in quibus recensentur omnis generis... (Ranke 321.24 G35f), 1765; OA12 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified slips, found laid in Joannis Caspari Barthel... (Ranke 348 B28 t.2 and t.3), OA12 (Box 1)
- X Series
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 1 March 1865; X1 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 5 March 1865; X2 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 31 March [no year], X3 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 1 December 1865; X4 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 1 November 1869; X5 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 14 December 1869; X6 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to Amelia Graves, 7 March 1865; X7 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John and Amelia Graves, 1 March 1864; X8 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, undated; X9 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 29 October 1865; X10 (Box 1)
  - Envelope addressed to Helena Graves, 29 August 1843; X11 (Box 1)
  - Envelope addressed to Helena Graves, 17 August 1843, X12 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke, envelope only, to Rev. Graves, 16 July 1865; X13 (Box 1)
  - Business card of Samuel Page, notary public and stock broker, with stock quotes for Helena Graves; date on verso, 16 October 1843; X14 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 15 March 1865; X15 (Box 1)
  - Clara Ranke to John Graves, 22 March 1865; X16 (Box 1)
  - Envelope containing newspaper clippings about Leopold von Ranke's death, 24 May 1886; X17 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to Charles Graves, 27 June 1865; X18 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to Robert Graves, 3 July 1857; X19 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to John Graves, 22 June 1865; X20 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to "My Dearest Schoolmistress", 17 August 1843; X21 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to "My dearest friend", 28 July 1843; X22 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to Robert Graves, 24 June 1857; X23 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to John Graves, 3 August 1856; X24 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to Charles Graves, 16 June 1855; X25 (Box 1)
  - Leopold Ranke to. Clara Ranke, 17 October 1868; X26 (Box 1)
  - Wilhelm Horning, printed funeral oration for General Fieldmarshal Edwin von Manteuffel, 21 June 1885; X27 (Box 1)
  - G. Kopp, printed funeral oration for General Fieldmarshal Edwin von Manteuffel, 21 June 1885; X28 (Box 1)
- Y Series
  - Unidentified letter, Y1 (Box 2)
  - "Extract from Madame von Ranke's letter giving an account of the Jubilee at Berlin on the 20 February 1867 being the 50th anniversary of her husband's connection with the University there", Y2 (Box 2)
  - Contract wherein Aaron Graves leased farm land to Simon S. Yoder in the township of Middlefield, Ohio, 1 April 1896; Y3 (Box 2)
  - Helena Graves to her father, 18 December 1817; Y4 (Box 2)
  - Clara Graves (Ranke), drawing of Telessin Hall, Y5 (Box 2)
  - Clara Graves (Ranke), drawing of Telessin Hall, Y6 (Box 2)
  - One of her grandfathers to Clara Graves (Ranke), 29 May 1825; Y7 (Box 2)
  - Riddles and jokes for children, Y8 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to John C. Graves, undated; Y9 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous hymns, Y10 (Box 2)
  - A puzzle attributed to Clara Graves (Ranke), Y11 (Box 2)
  - Drawing of a castle, Y12 (Box 2)
  - Copy of a letter from Josephine to Napoleon Bonaparte, Y13 (Box 2)
  - One of her grandfathers to Clara Graves (Ranke), Y14 (Box 2)
  - Clara Graves to Mrs. Graves, in Italian, 7 February 1823; Y15 (Box 2)
  - "Copy of a letter from Princess Charlotte of Wales to the Hon. George Keppel", 1809; Y16 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Graves (Ranke), Y17 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Graves (Ranke), Y18 (Box 2)
  - "A copy of a very old letter from Mrs. (Anna) Grant authoress of letters from the mountains etc. in answer to a letter from Mr. Chalmers regarding a particular account of his situation for the information of some Ladies.", Y19 (Box 2)
  - H.S. Parkman, engraving of Thomas T. Biddulph, Y20 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified note, 19 June 1817; Y21 (Box 2)
  - Printed page of characters for a drama, 1820; Y22; date based on watermark (Box 2)
  - Poem, Y23 (Box 2)
  - Thomas More, poem titled, "Lady Byron's answer to her Lord's Farewe1l.", Y24 (Box 2)
  - List of poets and puzzles, Y25 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "Quadrilling", Y26 (Box 2)
  - Poems, Y27 (Box 2)
  - "Ossian's address to the Sun from Thomas Travers Burke's versification of the poem of 'Carthon'", Y28 (Box 2)
  - "Charade", Y29 (Box 2)
  - "An Hieroglyphic Puzzle", Y30 (Box 2)
  - Poem, Y31 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "On Reading Miss Woom's Album", Y32 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "On seeing on a Lady's Neck a French Watch Which had Stopped", Y33 (Box 2)
  - Poem, Y34 (Box 2)
  - "Anagram of Walterus Scotus", Y35 (Box 2)
  - Elena Graves, letter in Russian, Y36 (Box 2)
  - Edward Coxe, poem titled, "The Fable of the Crab", Y37 (Box 2)
  - Thomas More, poem titled, "On the Death of Her Royal Highness the Princess Charlotte of Wales", Y38 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "Lines on the Death of the Princess Charlotte", Y39 (Box 2)
  - "Curious Coincidences Respecting the Letter C, as Connected with the Lamented Princess Charlotte.", Y40 (Box 2)
  - "Sent correspondence", Y41 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Hemans, inscription composed for the funeral monuments of John James Wedderburn (died 11 October 1810) and George Wedderburn (died 23 May 1823), Y42 (Box 2)
  - "Sonnet on a Scene in Ely Cathedral", Y43 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Mrs. Graves, includes a copy of Thomas Moore's poem, "A Canadian Boat-Song", 12 September 1806; Y44 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "The Namesakes", Y45 (Box 2)
  - "The Cesar's Discovery of the Bodies of Charles the 1st and Henry the 8th in the Same Vault at Windsor.", Y46 (Box 2)
  - A riddle, Y47 (Box 2)
  - Riddles, Y48 (Box 2)
  - "Epigrammes, calembours, et jeux des mots sur Bonaparte", Y49 (Box 2)
  - Drawing 1n pencil, Y50 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned letter to L.C. Graves, 10 March 1843; Y51 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "The Husband's Complaint", Y52 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "Home", Y53 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned note to Miss Graves, containing a newspaper clipping, postmarked 1830; Y54 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Miss Graves, Y55 (Box 2)
  - "Aunt Annie" to Clara Graves (Ranke), undated; Y56 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Graves (Ranke), 1837; Y57 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Graves (Ranke), Y58 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "On a Port Never Seen", Y59 (Box 2)
  - Poem addressed to Miss Graves, "On a strain of Music Never Heard", Y60 (Box 2)
  - "Song for Rousseau's Dream by Uncle Percival", Y61 (Box 2)
  - Dolly Swainson to Agey Braithwaite, undated; Y62 (Box 2)
  - Agey Braithwaite to Dolly Swainson, "A Westmoreland Note", undated; Y63 (Box 2)
  - H. Edmunds, "The Cataract of Ladore", 12 December 1835; Y64 (Box 2)
  - Robert Percival Graves, poem "composed on the Interment [of] John Bolton Esq. in Bowness Churchyard March 9th 1837", Y65 (Box 2)
  - N. Briggs to Miss Graves, 6 October 1839; Y66 (Box 2)
  - A sprig of Kenilworth ivy, Y67 (Box 2)
  - Charles Graves, sonnet to Wordsworth, 1833 or 1834; Y68 (Box 2)
  - "Remarks on English Ladies by a Roman Translated by H.C.G. (Helena Clarissa Graves)", Y69 (Box 2)
  - "Specimens from a Patent Pocket Dictionary", Y70 (Box 2)
  - Marin de la voye, poem addressed to Mademoiselle Graves, Y71 (Box 2)
  - "Schiller to the Ideal", Y72 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "Das fugal das Gud'uhl", Y73 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "Zwischen Pisa und Livorno" [Between Pisa and Livorno], Y74 (Box 2)
  - Robert Percival Graves, printed poem, "To Mrs. Fletcher on the Seventy-fifth Anniversary of Her Birth-day", Y75 (Box 2)
  - Alfred A. Percival, to Clara Graves (Ranke), 12 October 1843; Y76 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned letter to Helena Graves, Y77 (Box 2)
  - Clara Graves (Ranke), poem "To Aloe", 21 December 1843; Y78 (Box 2)
  - Translation addressed to Clara Graves (Ranke) of "Müde bin ich" [Tired am I], Y79 (Box 2)
  - Translation of the German song "The Wanderer", Y80 (Box 2)
  - T.W. Zinkheisen, "Fragment eines Briefes aus London vom 3 November" [Fragment of a letter from London on 3 November], Y81 (Box 2)
  - Clara Ranke, "A thought on the Minister Eickhorn's Birthday, 2 March 1847; Y82 (Box 2)
  - Robert Percival Graves, poem "To My Friend, T.H. Bethamley Esq. on the Christening of his Son and my Godson Arthur Thomas Bethamley", 15 March 1847; Y83 (Box 2)
  - Memorandum about names, Y84 (Box 2)
  - "Hymn for a Sick Child", Y85 (Box 2)
  - Clara Ranke to Leopold Ranke, undated; Y86 (Box 2)
  - Poem, "To Otto's Father", Y87 (Box 2)
  - Richard Brodkin to unnamed recipient, undated; Y88 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned [Lola Muntie?] to Clara Ranke, Y89 (Box 2)
  - "The Civil Governor of Guernsey, extract from Mr. Carry's letter about Robert", Y90 (Box 2)
  - "Extract from a letter written by the Rev'd G. Gisborne to his grandson", 13 March 1845; Y91 (Box 2)
  - "Dublin Improvement Bill", 23 February 1847; Y92 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, Y93 (Box 2)
  - The same, Y94 (Box 2)
  - Pio del Bufalo della Valle to Helena Graves, 4 April 1844; Y95 (Box 2)
  - Giovanni Carlo Muti to Helena Graves, 1 September 1845; Y96 (Box 2)
  - Giovanni Carlo Muti to Helena Graves, 28 December 1846; Y97 (Box 2)
  - Anagrams, Y98 (Box 2)
  - Receipt for the purchase of A History of the English Navy, 19 December 1862; Y99 (Box 2)
  - Poems in English translation, "Über allen Gipfeln" and "Wer nie sein Brod mit Thränen aus Wilhelm Meister", Y100 (Box 2)
  - Otto Opel to Leopold Ranke, in Ra 940.7 O61 1bd.) (copy), 23 May 1872; Y101 (Box 2)
  - Leopold Ranke to George Reimer (copy; original at University of Illinois), 26 January 1824; Y102 (Box 2)
  - "A Prayer to be used for a sick child", Y103 (Box 2)
  - Poems collected by Helena Graves's mother, Y104 (Box 2)
  - Robert Percival Graves to unidentified recipient, 1846; Y105 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned note, October 28, Y106 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Dora Wordsworth, 12 August 1838; Y107 (Box 2)
  - Charles Tennyson Graves, poem, Y108 (Box 2)
  - Katherine Hyde Clarke, poem "The River of God", Y109 (Box 2)
  - "A forest scene from the vision of Dante", Y110 (Box 2)
  - "Song from Tennyson's 'Rimes': "O Swallow, Swallow flying South", Y111 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned valentine, Y112 (Box 2)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 21 October 1847; Y113 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, 1843; Y114; date based on watermark (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y115 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y116 (Box 2)
  - John Graves to his mother, 13 September 1844; Y117 (Box 2)
  - "Nursery matters", Y118 (Box 2)
  - "Lines written by Charles when he was very young", Y119 (Box 2)
  - Untitled story, Y120 (Box 2)
  - William Wordsworth, poem, "On the Projected Kendal and Windermere Rail-way", Y121 (Box 2)
  - List of frescos in Rome, Y122 (Box 2)
  - "Extract of a letter from Colonel Stack commanding the 3d Bombay Light Cavalry to Sir Ephrim Stannas" recommending Lt. John Graves, Y123 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y124 (Box 2)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y125-127 (Box 3)
  - "Conversations with Clara", Y128 (Box 3)
  - "Prayer to be used by a Woman During her being With child", Y129 (Box 3)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y130 (Box 3)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y131 (Box 3)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y132 (Box 3)
  - "Extract from a letter of Doctor Amoldo to Rev. Heam", Y133 (Box 3)
  - "A Thanksgiving Prayer", Y134 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to one of her sons, undated; Y135 (Box 3)
  - Anecdotes about medicines, Y136 (Box 3)
  - Note on children's health and exercise, Y137 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 25 September [no year], Y138 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y139 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 3 January 1848; Y140 (Box 3)
  - "Extracts from the life of Canova the Italian sculptor", Y141 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 2 June [no year], Y142 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 8 March [no year], Y143 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 29 March [no year], Y144 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 3 July 1848; Y145 (Box 3)
  - Advice on medicine for and care of infants, Y146 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 14 June 1847; Y147 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, April 1848, Y148 (Box 3)
  - "Advertisement copied from the Athenium" and gossip about Lola Montes [Montez], Y149 (Box 3)
  - Information on Lola Montes [Montez], Y150 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 12 December [no year], Y151 (Box 3)
  - Cecilia Hodgson to Helena Graves and Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 8 February 1849; Y152 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y153 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y154 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 11 January [no year], Y155 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y156 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 18 July [no year], Y157 (Box 3)
  - He1ena Graves to Clara Ranke, 18 May 1848; Y158 (Box 3)
  - Unsigned to Helena Graves, 7 August 1846; Y159 (Box 3)
  - Poem, "Lord Teach Us to Pray", Y160 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke with extracts from other letters, undated; Y161 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 1 May [no year], Y162 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 8 June [no year], Y163 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y164 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 4 September [no year], on stationery engraved with a portrait of Jenny Lind, Y165-166 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y167 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves' "Prescriptions for Clara", 29 March 1847; Y168 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 13 December 1849; Y169 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Leopold Ranke, 14 January [no year], Y170 (Box 3)
  - "From 'The Atlas' newspaper -- a paragraph from the critique upon Ranke's History of Serbia", Y171 (Box 3)
  - He1ena Graves to Otto Ranke, Y172 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y173 (Box 3)
  - William Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 9 October 1843; Y174 (Box 3)
  - Robert Graves to Clara Ranke, 11 September 1844; Y175 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y176 (Box 3)
  - William Percival Graves (?) to Clara Ranke, 15 December 1845; Y177 (Box 3)
  - Robert Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y178-179 (Box 3)
  - Amelia Graves to Clara Ranke, 9 November 1846; Y180 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 3 April 1845; Y181 (Box 3)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 20 August [no year], Y182 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 18 March 1848; Y183 (Box 3)
  - Note in Ranke's hand with information on other historians and faculty at Berlin, Y184 (Box 3)
  - "Impromptu verses nursing little Otto sung to God Save the King", Y185 (Box 3)
  - Biographical note in French about Leopold Ranke, Y186 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 15 May 1847; Y187 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 10 July 1847; Y188 (Box 3)
  - Robert and Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 29 October 1848; Y189 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 26 January 1848; Y190-191 (Box 3)
  - "Copy of letter from R.P.G. (Robert Percival Graves) to Mr. Dilke, editor of the Athenaeum", 26 January 1848; Y192 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 17 April 1849; Y193 (Box 3)
  - Helena and Robert Graves to Clara Ranke, 28 May 1849; Y194 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to Clara Ranke, 3 June 1850; Y195 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 12 February 1850; Y196 (Box 3)
  - Harriett M. Owen to Robert Percival Graves, 9 April 1847; Y197 (Box 3)
  - Harriett M. Owen to Robert Percival Graves, 8 April 1847; Y198 (Box 3)
  - Harriett M. Owen to Clara Ranke, 20 July 1844; Y199 (Box 3)
  - Harriett M. Owen to Clara Ranke, 10 March 1848; Y200 (Box 3)
  - Harriett M. O¡¿en to Clara Ranke, 19 October 1847; Y201 (Box 3)
  - C. Hemans to Clara Ranke, 12 October [no year], Y202 (Box 3)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, October, Y203 (Box 3)
  - Fanny Pritt to Clara Ranke, 2 March 1847; Y204-5 (Box 3)
  - C.K. Richards to Clara Ranke, 9 September [no year], Y206 (Box 3)
  - D. Lloyd to Clara Ranke, undated; Y207 (Box 3)
  - C.K. Richards to Clara Ranke, 30 July 1848; Y208 (Box 3)
  - Harriet Miller to Clara Ranke, 7 December 1849; Y209 (Box 3)
  - Robert Percival Graves to John Graves, 24 April 1850; Y210 (Box 3)
  - Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 23 April 1849; Y211 (Box 3)
  - Post script to the above letter, Y212 (Box 3)
  - M.L. Gisborne to Clara Ranke, 26 December 1849; Y213 (Box 3)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 25 August 1849; Y214 (Box 3)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 20 October 1845; Y215 (Box 3)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 9 October 1845; Y216 (Box 3)
  - Ranke's notes taken from Joseph Harnmer-Purgstall, Geschichte der Ilchane das ist der Mongolen in Persien...mit neun Beilagen und neun Stammtafelm (Darmstadt, 1842-43) 2:216-17, Y216a (Box 3)
  - Ranke's notes taken frorn Thomas Arnold, History of Rome (London 1840-43), 2:328, Y216b (Box 3)
  - Charles Graves to Clara Ranke, 2 February 1850; Y217 (Box 3)
  - Selina Graves to Clara Ranke, 2 April 1850; Y218 (Box 3)
  - Letter fragment, Y219 (Box 3)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, undated; Y220 (Box 3)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 18 February 1850; Y221 (Box 3)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 26 February 1850; Y222 (Box 3)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 30 April 1850; Y223 (Box 3)
  - John T. Graves to Leopold Ranke, 2 October 1843; Y224 (Box 3)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 25 December 1849; Y225 (Box 3)
  - Ame1ia Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y226 (Box 4)
  - Garya y Maasaaffa to the Rankes, 15 February 1850; Y227 (Box 4)
  - Fragment in Ranke's hand, Y228 (Box 4)
  - Rosine von Wintgen to the Rankes, 1 November 1850; Y229 (Box 4)
  - A. von Muding to Leopold Ranke, 11 February 1850; Y230 (Box 4)
  - UnknownauthortoLeopoldRanke,28 April 1850, Y231 (Box 4)
  - Ame1la Graves to Clara Ranke, 20 April 1850; Y232 (Box 4)
  - Unsigned to Clara Ranke, undated; Y233 (Box 4)
  - "Ode to Ranke" by Walden, 20 January 1850; Y234 (Box 4)
  - F.N.V. to Leopold Ranke, 18 May 1850; Y235 (Box 4)
  - Leopold Ranke to Clara Ranke, 13 October 1848; Y236 (Box 4)
  - Mary Mohl to Clara Ranke, 15 May [no year], Y237 (Box 4)
  - (Mary Mohl) to Clara Ranke, undated; Y238 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 28 April 1850; Y239 (Box 4)